Guide to the Josiah William Bailey Papers, 1833-1967, bulk 1900-1946 RL.00065
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Josiah William Bailey papers
1833-1967
1900-1946
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Bailey, Josiah William, 1873-1946
RL.00065
270 Linear Feet 539 boxes
The collection houses the personal and professional papers of Josiah William Bailey (1873-1946), Baptist layman, Raleigh attorney, and United States Senator. Chiefly consists of correspondence and print material, as well as smaller amounts of financial records, clippings, volumes, broadsides, photographs, and memorabilia dating from 1833 through 1967, with most items dating from 1900 through 1946. The collection documents Bailey's family, personal, religious, and professional life. Generally, papers prior to Bailey's election to the U.S. Senate in 1931 reflect North Carolina's legal, political, religious, agricultural, social, and economic issues. After 1931, material chiefly pertains to national affairs. Significant topics include: state and national elections and campaigns in the 1920s and 1930s; national defense and the military; veterans; the effects of the Depression on southern states and the U.S. economy and society in general; labor issues; Prohibition; the court system; taxation; the development of the Blue Ridge Parkway and other parks; agriculture in the Southern States; and the New Deal of the Roosevelt Administration. Legal papers offer a sample of case files from Bailey's law office, including a 1920s case involving W.V. Guerard of the Klu Klux Klan. Outgoing personal correspondence contains many references to national and regional issues as well as personal exchanges.
Approximately 422,400 itemss
Biographical Note
Chronology
1873 Josiah William Bailey born, September 14; Warrenton, N.C.
1877 Bailey's father, Christopher Thomas Bailey, appointed editor of the Biblical Recorder; family moves to Raleigh, N.C.
1880-1889 Bailey attends Raleigh Township Graded Schools and Raleigh Male Academy.
1893 Received B.A. degree from Wake Forest College.
1893-1907 Edited Biblical Recorder. As editor, Bailey emphasized the need for improved public school conditions in N.C. and advocated state aid to public schools.
1896-1900 Member, State Board of Agriculture.
1900 election Supported disfranchisement of Negroes, Furnifold Simmons for Senate, and Charles B. Aycock for governor.
1903-1907 Chairman, N.C. Anti-Saloon League. Fought to establish local option. Opposed national prohibition. Resigned when League resolved to support state prohibition.
1907-1908 Studied law under Samuel French Mordecai, Trinity College. Admitted to the bar, began practice with Wesley N. Jones.
1908 Elector at Large.
1909-1911 Member, Board of Education, Wake County.
1911-1913 Chairman, State Child Labor Committee.
1912 election Supported Woodrow Wilson for President and Locke Craig for governor. F.M. Simmons re-elected U.S. Senator.
1913-1910 Appointed by President Wilson to be Collector for Internal Revenue for N.C. Eastern District.
1913 Governor Craig appointed Bailey to N.C. Constitutional Commission. Commission recommended voting reform, court changes, tax reform, required school term.
1914 Assumed leadership of liberal faction of State Democratic Party. Suggestions of this faction defeated by subsequent state convention.
1916 Married Edith Walker Pou.
1917 Addressed N.C. General Assembly in behalf of women's suffrage.
1919-1921 Internal Revenue Collector for N.C.
1919-1920 Represented interests of the Farmers' Union before the N.C. General Assembly, opposing increased property taxes.
1921 Returned to legal practice full-time with James Hinton Pou.
1924 Candidate for governor. Defeated in primary by Angus Wilton McLean whom Simmons supported
1928 Supported Alfred E. Smith for the presidency, O. Max Gardner for governor.
1930 Candidate for U.S. Senate; defeated Simmons in primary and won election with record-breaking majority.
1932 Advocated currency control. Suggested reducing administrative expenses, but supported public works appropriations
1932 election Actively supported Roosevelt in North Carolina.
1933 Opposed Agricultural Adjustment Act.
1936 Re-elected to Senate.
1937 Strongly opposed "court packing" bill. Supported Neutrality Act. Emerged as key Figure in Senate conservative alliance.
1938 Opposed Fair Labor Standards Act. Became chairman of Commerce Committee.
1940 Supported Selective Service Bill.
1941 Supported Lend-Lease. Reversing earlier position, advocated intervention.
1942 Re-elected to Senate.
1945 Supported ratification of the United Nations Charter.
1946 Died Dec. 15 in Raleigh, N.C.
Committee Assignments
Committee Assignments
Claims: 1931-1944 72nd-78th Congresses (Chairman, 1933-1938)
Commerce: 1931-1946 72nd-79th Congresses (Chairman, 1939-1946)
Finance: 1935 74th Congress (Apparently Bailey was on this committee only briefly)
Interstate Commerce: 1933-1934 73rd Congress
Post Office and Post Roads: 1931-1946 72nd-79th Congresses
Special Committee on the Conservation of Wildlife Resources: 1933-1946 73rd-79th Congresses
Special Committee to Investigate Conditions in the Merchant Marine (Chairman): 1939-1944 76th-78th Congresses
Family Information
Family Information
Josiah William Bailey
Josiah William Bailey
Father: Christopher Thomas Bailey
Mother: Annie Sarah (Bailey) Bailey
Sister: Sallie C. Bailey (married Wesley N. Jones; children: Annie Railey,Sallie W., William B.)
Brother: Christopher Thomas Bailey, Jr. (married Mary Himbish)
Brother: Edmund Lamar Bailey
Brother: Bayard Yates Bailey (died in infancy)
Edith Walker Pou
Father: James Hinton Pou
Mother: Annie Walker Pou
Children of Josiah William and Edith Pou Bailey
James Hinton Pou (b. 1917)
Annie Elizabeth (b. 1920)
Josiah William, Jr. (b. 1922)
Edith Pou (b. 1925)
Sallie (b. 1927)
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Josiah Bailey papers were received as a gift by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1957 from the Bailey family.
Collection Overview
Collection comprises the personal and professional papers of Josiah William Bailey (1873-1946), noted Baptist layman, Raleigh attorney, and United States Senator. The material covers many aspects of Bailey's life and career and provides rich information on North Carolina and the United States in the first half of the twentieth century, particularly for the Depression years and World War II.
The papers are comprised chiefly of correspondence and supporting printed material, although there are also financial records, clippings, volumes, broadsides, photographs, and memorabilia, dating from 1833 through 1967, with most items falling in the period from 1900 through 1946.
The collection documents Josiah W. Bailey's family, personal, religious, and professional life and indicates the wide range of his intellectual interests throughout his adult years. Generally, papers prior to Bailey's election to the United States Senate in 1930 reflect North Carolina's legal, political, religious, agricultural, social, and economic issues. During the senatorial years, material pertaining to national affairs predominates. Topics chiefly relate to national defense, the effects of the Depression on Southern States and the U.S. economy and society in general; labor issues; prohibition; the development of the Blue Ridge Parkway and other parklands; the state and Supreme Court systems; agriculture in the Southern States; and the New Deal of the Roosevelt Administration.
The chronological division between the Pre-Senatorial Series and the Senatorial Series was established at December 31, 1930. There is occasional overlap among topical files within a series (such as that among Agriculture, Taxation, and Taxation: Revaluation in the Pre-Senatorial Series) or between series in some cases. When possible, cross references and other notes have been provided in the inventory. The researcher, however, should be aware of these relationships as they apply to specific research topics.
Much of Bailey's outgoing correspondence consists of form letters and perfunctory acknowledgments, but there are also many lengthy and articulate letters. It should be noted that the correspondence in the Personal Series is comprised mainly of family letters, many of which are informative about political issues of the day. Letters from Bailey to his wife, Edith Pou Bailey, and to his father-in-law, James Hinton Pou, are particularly informative.
Agriculture and state -- Southern States -- History -- 20th century; Baptists -- North Carolina; Depressions -- 1929 -- United States; Labor unions -- United States -- 1930-1970; Lawyers -- North Carolina -- Correspondence; Legislators -- North Carolina -- Correspondence; New Deal, 1933-1939; Political campaigns -- North Carolina; North Carolina -- Economic conditions; North Carolina -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950; Southern States -- Economic conditions -- 1918-; Southern States -- Religious life and customs; Southern States -- Social conditions -- 1865-1945; United States -- Defenses -- Decision making; United States -- Economic conditions -- 1918-1945; United States -- Military policy -- 20th century; United States -- Politics and government -- 1901-1953; Broadsides; Legal files; Photographs; United States. Congress. Senate; Democratic Party (N.C.)
- Correspondence Series, 1833-1963, 18 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Family correspondence consists largely of letters to and from family members. For the pre-Senatorial period, there are Items from Bailey's friends and some personal correspondence of Edith Pou Bailey. Although some of these letters are of merely passing interest, others are quite detailed on subjects of research interest. A small folder of personal printed material (programs and other memorabilia) has been placed at the end of this main correspondence section.
  Alphabetical correspondence includes letters to and from several individuals with whom Bailey corresponded frequently. There may also be isolated letters from these individuals in other parts of the collection. Arranged chronologically by day within each section.
  Correspondence related to The Baptist Church and Its Institutions In North Carolina includes letters to and from ministers and church officials as well as representatives of church-affiliated institutions such as Wake Forest University, Mars Hill College, and Chowan College. Also contains material on the organization and operation or the Biblical Recorder and correspondence of its editors Livingston Johnson, J. S. Farmer, J. C. Slemp, and L. L. Carpenter. Other correspondents include the following: J. W. Lynch; William B. Royall; R. L. Moore; William Louis Poteat; Frances P. Gaines; J. A. Campbell; Joseph Bascomb Huff; Preston S. Vann; Louis D. Newton, editor of the Christian Index (Atlanta, Ga.); Robert H. Pitt, editor Herald (Richmond, Va.); and Archibald Johnson, editor of Charity and Children. Of particular interest is the exchange of letters between Bailey and John E. White, a Baptist educator and preacher in North Carolina, South Carolina, and Georgia.
  - Inventory & Introduction; Correspondence, 1833-ca. 1891, June (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1891-1894 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1895-1904 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1905-1912, May (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1912, June-1913, Aug. (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1913, Sept.-1915 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1915-1920 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1920, Aug.-1932 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1933-1934 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1935-1936 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1936-1943 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1943-1944 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, 1945-1963, undated (Box 13)
  - Correspondence, undated; Printed Material; Names (Benson, E.C.) (Box 14)
  - Names (Meekins, I.M.; Paschal, G.W.; Ruffin, J.M.) (Box 15)
  - Names (Ruffin, J.M.); Baptist Church, 1880's-1927 (Box 16)
  - Baptist Church, 1927-1941 (Box 17)
  - Baptist Church, 1941-1947; Writings & Addresses (Religious) (Box 18)
- Writings and Addresses Series, 1819-1913, 5 boxes
  Manuscript notes, drafts and corrections, typescripts, and some printed copies of writings, addresses, and statements.
  The first part of this group consists of religious writings, most of which are undated (5 folders). Some topics include:
  Does the Christian Religion Stand the Test (1920)
  The Inadequacy of Modern Christianity to the Modern World
  Jesus' View of Wealth (1922)
  Ideals of the Christian College (1923)
  Historical Testimonies to the Baptist Contribution of Religious Liberty (1928)
  After Twenty-five Years (1932; on the Biblical Recorder)
  The Common Sense of Jesus of Nazareth (1934)
  The Basis of Representation in Baptist Conventions
  Jesus - An Appeal to Reason
  Victories of the Bible
  The Divine Method of Culture
  The remaining writings and addresses are on miscellaneous subjects and include sketches of prominent individuals, commencement addresses and other occasional speeches, addresses, and notes on political philosophy and American history in general. In most cases, especially for writings prepared after 1930, Items on specific subject are found in the appropriate subject category in the Senatorial or Pre-Senatorial Series.
  Miscellaneous writings include the following:
  1890-1900
  School essays; address for the class of 1893, Wake Forest College
  1900-1920
  Sketch of Archibald Murphy
  Decision Day Address, University of North Carolina
  The Heritage of the Great War
  Our Task of Happiness
  Notes for speeches during World War I
  1920s
  Thoughts on the Financial Depression (1921)
  Times that Try Men's Souls
  Economic Conditions in Rural N. C.
  Condition of the Farmers in N. C.
  Sketch of Wesley Norwood Jones
  Sketch of Dr. William B. Royall
  A Case for the Cardinal
  On the Constitution
  Henry Groves Connor --Address upon portrait presentation
  Law Enforcement
  1930s
  Our Duty to Preserve the Character of Our Republic (before the Southern Society of New York City)
  Spiritual Values
  The Spirit of the American Revolution
  The Present Outlook (1932)
  Mercer University Centennial Address
  What is the Matter with N. C.?
  Letters of a Coat-Tail Congressman, Selected By his Private Secretary (satire by Bailey later submitted to the Saturday Evening Post)
  Novom Orderum Seculares (to New England Society of Charleston)
  North Carolina Signers of the Federal Constitution
  Sketch of Judge William Gaston
  The Major Decisions of President Roosevelt
  Advertising North Carolina
  Dominant Ideas of the Constitution (to the Economic Club, Worcester, Mass.)
  The National Gold-Fish Bowl by B. Pshaw (satire about Justice Hugo L. Black)
  The South as a National Problem
  Sketch of W. W. Vass
  The Democratic Process (commencement address, Colby College)
  The President Draws the Line (race question and immigration)
  The Status of the U. S. At the Present Time (1939)
  1940s
  The intervention issue
  The Price of Peace
  Our Republic--It Must be Preserved
  Robert E. Lee
  Bricks Without Straw: Fabian Socialism in the United States
  The South at the Crossroads
  The Second American Revolution (submitted to the Saturday Evening Post)
  What is the American Way of Life
  Notes and fragments, poetry by Bailey, writings by members of the Bailey family, and some writings by other individuals complete the Writings and Addresses section.
  - Writings & Addresses, 1890-1932 (Box 19)
  - Writings & Addresses, 1933-1940 (Box 20)
  - Writings & Addresses, 1941-1945, undated (Box 21)
  - Writings & Addresses, Notes, Poetry, Misc.; Financial, ca. 1900-1913 (Box 22)
- Financial Materials Series, 1914-1927, 6 boxes
  The first section consists of correspondence pertaining to real estate, investments, and other financial matters. Material is arranged roughly by year. After this chronological sequence, there are separate categories for insurance policy summary, income tax returns, the Bland Hotel' and the Andrew Johnson Hotel.
  - Financial, ca. 1914-1932 (Box 23)
  - Financial, 1932-1936 (Box 24)
  - Financial, 1937-1946, Insurance, Tax (Box 25)
  - Financial, Tax, Bland Hotel (Box 26)
  - Financial, Andrew Johnson Hotel; Invitations (Box 27)
- Invitations, Engagements, and Memorabilia Series, 1911-1946, 10 boxes
  Arrangement note
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Invitations, 1911-1932 (Box 28)
  - Invitations, 1933-1935 (Box 29)
  - Invitations, 1935-1937 (Box 30)
  - Invitations, 1937-1938 (Box 31)
  - Invitations, 1939-1940 (Box 32)
  - Invitations, 1940-1941 (Box 33)
  - Invitations, 1941-1943 (Box 34)
  - Invitations, 1943-1946 (Box 35)
  - Invitations, 1946, undated; Volumes (Box 36)
- Volumes Series, 1 box
  - Volumes (Box 37)
- Legal Materials Series, ca. 1900-1940
  - General Subseries (Box 37-38)
    Correspondence relating to various aspects of Bailey's law practice. Often routine. Includes some letters of advice to young lawyers. Unarranged, about 5 folders.
  - Case Files Subseries
    Arranged alphabetically, these case files represent a sample of files in Bailey's law office.
    - Alexander, Mrs. Addie L. (ca. 1920-1925) (Box 38)
    - Applications (Box 38)
    - Associated Theaters Inc. (ca. 1923-1925) (Box 38)
    - Bailey, Martha (ca. 1929-1930) (Box 38)
    - Bailey, R. W. (ca. 1927) (Box 38)
    - Bailey family (see also Jones, Leigh, and Pou)
      - Bailey, Annie S. Will. (Box 38)
      - Bailey, Christopher Thomas (1915-1920).see also Personal Series. (Box 38)
      - Bailey, Edith Pou (ca. 1924-1931). Property statements, indentures, and lega1 affairs. See also Bailey, Mr. and Mrs., Josiah William. (Box 38)
      - Bailey, Helen Leigh (ca. 1914-1926). Bailey's guardianship of his niece. (Box 38)
      - Bailey, Helen Leigh (continued) (Box 39)
      - Bailey, Mr. and Mrs. Josiah William. Miscellaneous family material. (Box 39)
      - Bailey, Robert Cooper. Concerns Bailey's guardianship. (Box 40)
      - Bailey, Sallie Cooper (1910-1918) (Box 40)
      - Bailey, William E, Estate, ca. 1905-1929. (Box 40)
      - Brogden, W. L. (ca. 1903-1931) Bailey handled severa1 legal matters for Brogden. (Box 40)
    - Buell, G. I. (ca. 1928-1929) Involves Falling Springs Lime Co., Inc., and a dispute over the use of limestone. (Box 41)
    - Bus Regulation (1924-1925) (Box 41)
    - Byrd, J. C. (ca. 1931) Concerns Harrison Lake Timber Co., Inc. (Box 41)
    - Byrd, W. G. (1926-1927). Bankruptcy case. (Box 41)
    - Cannon, Charles A v. J. W. Bailey, former Collector of Internal Revenue (1926). (Box 41)
    - Capitol Ice Company, Raleigh (ca. 1924-1927). Anti-trust problem; this company and others allegedly combined in restraint of trade (Box 41)
    - Carolina Academy (l926). Academy for boys. (Box 41)
    - Carolina Road Granite Co. (1929) (Box 42)
    - Carolina Theatres. Moving Pictures (1920-1930). (Box 42)
    - Chain Stores (Ca. 1930) (Box 42)
    - Chamber of Commerce (Raleigh). Efforts to locate Internal Revenue Service in North Carolina (ca. 1920 1930) (Box 42)
    - Charlotte Radio Station (1530) Power increase for radio station WBT. (Box 42)
    - Cherokee Brick Company (Raleigh, ca. 1918) (Box 42)
    - Cherokee Brick Company (1918-1930) (Box 43)
    - Clubs (includes Raleigh Country Club) (Box 43)
    - Cooperative Marketing (1921). North Carolina Cotton Growers' Co-Operative; Farmers' Union. (Box 43)
    - Cotten, Colonel R. R. and Bruce (1927). Concerns fraudulent indemnity bonds. (Box 43)
    - Cox, Reverend Francis A. (ca. 1930). Pertains to financial obligations of Cox, a missionary in China. (Box 43)
    - Coxe, T. C. v. Watts & Bailey (Box 43)
    - Criterion Advertising Company (1929). Dispute over a budget bill which taxed outdoor advertising. (Box 43)
    - DeWeese, Hamilton G. (1928). Concerns American Industrial Lenders Association and the introduction of a uniform small loan law into the North Carolina Legislature. (Box 43)
    - Dill, A. T. (1929-1930). Estate settlement. (Box 43)
    - Dixon, Thomas (1926-1927). Dixon's activities with the Wildacres development company and the Mount Mitchell Association of Arts and Sciences. (Box 43)
    - Drexel Furniture Company v. J. W. Bailey, Collector of Internal Revenue. (Box 43)
    - Duke heirs (1927). James B. Duke's will. (Box 43)
    - Durham Life Insurance, Co.--Radio (ca. 1927-1930) (Box 44)
      Deals with WPTF radio station owned by Durham Life. Correspondence and printed material presenting the station's attempts to get favorable ratings and more power from the Federal Radio Commission, Letters from educators at Shaw University, Duke University, Meredith College; from N. C. Congressmen; and from other prominent citizens. Also includes other legal affairs of Durham Life.
    - Enrollment and Disbarment, Committee On (1927-1928) (Box 44)
      Treasury Department committee which investigated a complaint against Bailey. The case was ultimately dismissed.
    - Erwin Cotton -Mills. Suit involving a patent for knot-tying implements. (Box 44)
    - Evans, W. F. (1927) (Box 45)
    - Farmers' Union (1921-1922) Incorporation and by-laws, etc. of The Farmers' Educational and Co-Operative Union of America, North Carolina Division. Includes a paper on farm tenancy in N. C. (Box 45)
    - Finch, S. E. v. Nash County Commissioners (1926) Relates to county-wide plan of school consolidation. (Box 45)
    - Fletcher, A. J. (Box 45)
    - Freight Rates--Fertilizer (ca. 1927), Includes various propositions, especially those relating to the interests of the N. C. Fertilizer Manufacturers Association. (Box 45)
    - Gaskill, D. B. bantcruptcy. (Box 45)
    - General Motors Corporation v. R. A. Doughton (1926). Conflict over licenses in N.C. (Box 45)
    - Glascock, Dr. H. W. (1928). Concerns an application for membership in the Wake County Medical Society and a resulting dispute. (Box 45)
    - Grainger, I. B. (1933). Relates to N. C. Bank and Trust Company. (Box 45)
    - Gregory, Margaret Overman (Mrs. Edwin Clarke). Pertains to the Robert E. Lee Memorial Foundation and the establishment of Stratford-on-the-Potomac. (Box 45)
    - Gulley and Tyler v. North Carolina (1925), Slight information on an interesting case in which a prisoner was flogged to death. Bailey's letters comment on convict guards on a road gang and on aspects of penal reform. (Box 45)
    - Hardy, Ira M. v. R. T. Wade, Coaster Publishing Company (ca. 1913-1922). (Box 45)
      A libel suit in which Bailey defended R. T. Wade, a Morehead City editor who had printed an editorial relating to financial matters at the N. C. School for the Feeble Minded for which Hardy was responsible. There are numerous clippings about the affair and correspondence with members of the school's Board of Trustees.
    - Hart Cotton Mills v. N. C. (1919-1931). Involves a claim. (Box 45)
    - Henderson, B. T. (ca. 1926). (Box 46)
    - Hicks v. Hicks (1926-1928). Divorce, alimony, and settlement case. (Box 46)
    - Highland Hospital (ca. 1928-1930). (Box 46)
      This file concerns a case, the State Board of Charities and Welfare, et al. v. Highland Hospital, Inc. and Dr. Robert S. Carroll: The case dealt with alleged immoral practices at and mismanagement of this hospital for the insane. Bailey defended Carroll.
    - Horton v. Horton (ca. 1922-1925). A divorce case involving wife-beating and neglect. Bailey defended the husband. (Box 47)
    - Internal Revenue (ca. 1921-1923) Papers pertaining to the end of Bailey's tenure as N.C. Collector of Internal Revenue. (Box 47)
    - Johnson, A. R. Do (Will, 1915; 1925-1931) Family legal affairs. Related to Cherokee Brick stock and some business disputes. (Box 47)
    - Johnson, Charles E. (ca. 1925-1926). Estate. (Box 47)
    - Johnson, Livingston (ca. 1925). Legal problems for the editor of the Biblical Recorder. Pertains to Darwinism and the evolution controversy and mentions the liberalism of Wake Forest University and William L. Poteat. (Box 47)